Guide to the American Federation of Musicians, Local 802 Records WAG.038
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Federation of Musicians, Local 802 Records
1921-2025, ongoing
1980-1999
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Federation of Musicians. Local 802
WAG.038
128.5 Linear Feet in 130 record cartons and 3 oversize folders.
19.2 Megabytes on 16 5 1/4 inch floppy disks
108 audiocassettes
13 websites in 13 archived websites.
The American Federation of Musicians, Local 802 (Associated Musicians of Greater New York) is the largest local of professional musicians in the world. As of 2011, it represents approximately 10,000 members in and around New York City. This collection consists of minutes of the executive and trial boards; departmental files; publications; and archived websites of Local 802.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into twelve series:
Series I: Executive Board Files, 1921-1999
Series II: President's Office Files, 1967-2003
Series III: Secretary's Office Files, 1960s-early 2000s
Series IV: Concert Department Files, 1950s-1990s
Series V: General Files, 1922-2010
Series VI: Organizing Department Files, 1980s-mid 2000s
Series VII: Public Relations and Political Action Office Files, late 1970s-2000
Series VIII: Show Files, 1960s-2004
Series IX: Trial Board Files, 1922-1990s
Series X: Oversized Material, 1921-1990s
Series XI: Photographs, undated
Series XII: Archived Websites, 2007-ongoing
Historical Note
The American Federation of Musicians, Local 802 (Associated Musicians of Greater New York) is the largest local of professional musicians in the world. As of 2011, it represents approximately 10,000 members in and around New York City. Members work in many fields of music: rock, rhythm and blues, jazz, Latin, concert, theater, club date, night club, ballroom and symphonic. They are also instrumentalists, copyists, arrangers, orchestral librarians, proofreaders, and editors. Additionally, Local 802 regularly demonstrates solidarity with fellow unions (particularly other entertainment unions) and is deeply involved in lobbying for union rights.
Local 802 was chartered on August 27, 1921. Its immediate predecessor was Local 310 of the AFM which held an independent charter from the State of New York. When Local 310 struck New York theaters against the wishes of AFM President Joseph N. Weber, the AFM set up the new Local 802.
From 1921-1934, Local 802 was under AFM trusteeship. A Congressional investigation into labor racketeering in 1934 prompted President Joseph N. Weber to permit the local to elect its own officers. By 1935, Local 802 was operating autonomously and opened its Long Island office. Members of Local 802 were employed wherever there was live musical entertainment. The union had a closed shop, oversaw all musicians' contracts and brought up members on charges whenever the union rules were violated. During the 1920's and 1930's this included not only symphony and opera performance, but theater orchestras, restaurants, night clubs, hotel ballrooms, catering establishments, parades, amusement parks, funerals and radio broadcasts.
In 1928, there were 15,500 members in Local 802; by 1940 the membership had grown to 21,300. At its height in the 1950's and 1960's, there were well over 30,000 members of Local 802.
The AFM was in litigation throughout the 1960's with the NLRB trying to settle the definitions of employer and employee in the entertainment business. Some adverse rulings made it difficult for the union to organize hotels and nightclubs. In the early 1960's, the side musicians who played single club dates objected to the slowness of bargaining benefits and wage improvements and demanded speedier negotiations with board leaders who were employers. At the same time many full time professional musicians felt that the union leadership was using the part time membership to maintain control.
A reform movement in Local 802 arose between 1964-1966, but was not successful in capturing any major leadership positions. Nevertheless, between 1966-1980, there were some important reforms: 802 contracts had to be ratified by membership; a credit union was established in 1967; an emergency relief fund was developed; and an active rank and file committee system was established in the by laws. Formal opposition to Local 802's leadership emerged in 1980, instigated by classical, club date and recording musicians. The caucus called itself the MEMBERS party, an acronym for Make Every Musician Benefit from Efficient Responsible Service. In the 1982 election the MEMBERS party, led by John Glasel, was able to make an almost clean sweep of the Executive Board.
One of the Glasel Administration's first acts was to create a department of public relations and legislative affairs under Judy West, who served as its director from 1983-2000. At the same time, organizing campaigns targeting jazz musicians were stepped up, becoming one of the major activities of Local 802 in the following two decades. Glasel was succeeded by Bill Moriarity the Secretary of Local 802 in 1993. In 2003, David Lennon was elected unopposed, but lost the 2006 election to Mary Landolfi. Tino Gagliardi was president of Local 802 from 2010-2018.
In the 2010s, Local 802 has worked to address the impact of computers and the internet on musicians' livelihoods. It was involved in attempting to solidify the financial condition of its parent union.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the American Federation of Musicians, Local 802, in 1978. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1978.005 and 1978.009. Additional materials were sent in 1985 and 2011. The accession numbers associated with these materials are 2011.100 and 2011.113. The accession number NPA.2003.024 is also associated with this collection. The most recent donation of materials was in 2018. The accession number associated with this donation is 2019.028
https://www.local802afm.org/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Archive. In 2015, this website was migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In May 2020, https://erf.local802afm.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2020.044. In December 2020, https://www.savenycmusicians.com/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2021.057. In January 2021, https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCw4IbKn0-Hr3V20wpva6zbg/videos was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2021.065. In May 2021, https://www.musicianscook.com/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2022.001. In February 2023, https://arc802.wordpress.com/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2023.020. In August 2023, http://www.fairshareformusicians.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2023.076. In Fall 2023, https://musiciansofnycb.com/, https://www.youtube.com/@musiciansofnewyorkcityball7808/videos/, and https://www.youtube.com/@Local802AFM/videos/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2023.088. In December 2023, https://afmfairshareformusicians.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2024.004. In September 2024, https://nypmusicians.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2024.050. In 2025, https://www.instagram.com/musicians_of_ny/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2025.098.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Content Note
The American Federation of Musicians, Local 802 Records (1921-2025, ongoing) consists of minutes, archived websites, departmental files, and publications of Local 802. These records document the local's struggles on behalf of New York City musicians. It also includes the minutes from the bi-weekly Executive Board and Trial Board meetings, as well as minutes from the more infrequent Regular Membership meetings. Executive Board deliberations and decisions include negotiations, concessions, membership status, local policy and expenditures. The Trial Board reviews infractions of the local laws and violations of wage scales, working conditions and other contractual matters for which members can be brought up on charges. Also included in the collection are records from the President's and Secretary's Offices, in addition to the Organizing, Public Relations and Political Action Offices.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Musicians -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Musicians -- New York (State) -- New York; Copyright infringement.; Labor unions -- Elections.; COVID-19 (Disease); Glasel, John; Moschel, Marvin; Moriarity, Bill; American Federation of Musicians; American Federation of Musicians. Local 802; American Federation of Musicians. Local 802; Ribot, Marc
- Series I: Executive Board Files, 1921-1999 (Box 2, Box 3, Box 1, Box 125, Box 126, Box 123, Box 124, Box 6, Box 122, Box 4, Box 5)
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Executive Board Files, 1921-1999 consists primarily of the minutes of the Executive Board meetings. The microfilm version of the minutes from 1921-1985 must be used.
  - Minutes, 1921-1923 (Film R-7438, Reel 1)
    General
    Originals in Box 1 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1924-1926 (Film R-7438, Reel 2)
  - Minutes, 1927-1928 (Film R-7438, Reel 3)
  - Minutes, 1929-1930 (Film R-7438, Reel 4)
  - Minutes, 1931-1932 (Film R-7438, Reel 5)
  - Minutes, 1933-1934 (Film R-7438, Reel 6)
  - Minutes, 1935 (Film R-7438, Reel 7)
  - Minutes, 1936 (Film R-7438, Reel 8)
    Originals in Box 2 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1937 (Film R-7438, Reel 9)
  - Minutes, 1938 (Film R-7438, Reel 10)
  - Minutes, 1939 (Film R-7438, Reel 11)
  - Minutes, Jan 1940-Jun 1940 (Film R-7438, Reel 12)
  - Minutes, Aug 1940-1941 (Film R-7438, Reel 13)
    Originals in Boxes 2-3 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, Jan 1942-Sep 1942 (Film R-7438, Reel 14)
    Originals in Box 3 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, Oct 1942-Jul 1943 (Film R-7438, Reel 15)
  - Minutes, Aug 1943-Aug 1944 (Film R-7438, Reel 16)
  - Minutes, Sep 1944-1945 (Film R-7438, Reel 17)
  - Minutes, 1946 (Film R-7438, Reel 18)
    Originals in Box 4 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1947 (Film R-7438, Reel 19)
  - Minutes, 1948 (Film R-7438, Reel 20)
  - Minutes, 1949 (Film R-7438, Reel 21)
  - Minutes, 1950 (Film R-7438, Reel 22)
  - Minutes, 1951 (Film R-7438, Reel 23)
    Originals in Boxes 4-5 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1952 (Film R-7438, Reel 24)
    Originals in Box 5 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1953 (Film R-7438, Reel 25)
  - Minutes, Jan 1954-Aug 1954 (Film R-7438, Reel 26)
  - Minutes, Aug 1954-Dec 1954 (Film R-7438, Reel 27)
  - Minutes, Jan 1955-Jun 1955 (Film R-7438, Reel 28)
  - Minutes, Jul 1955-Dec 1955 (Film R-7438, Reel 29)
    Originals in Box 6 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, Jan 1956-Jun 1956 (Film R-7438, Reel 30)
    Originals in Boxes 6 and 122 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, Jul 1956-Dec 1956 (Film R-7438, Reel 31)
  - Minutes, Jan 1957-Jun 1957 (Film R-7438, Reel 32)
  - Minutes, Jul 1957-1958 (Film R-7438, Reel 33)
  - Minutes, Jan 1959-Jun 1960 (Film R-7438, Reel 34)
  - Minutes, Jul 1960-1961 (Film R-7438, Reel 35)
  - Minutes, Jul 1962-1963 (Film R-7438, Reel 36)
  - Minutes, 1964-1965 (Film R-7438, Reel 37)
    Originals in Box 7 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1966-1967 (Film R-7438, Reel 38)
    Originals in Box 7 and 122 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1968-1969 (Film R-7438, Reel 39)
    Originals in Box 122 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1970-1971 (Film R-7438, Reel 40)
    Originals in Box 123 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1972-1973 (Film R-7438, Reel 41)
  - Minutes, 1974-1975 (Film R-7438, Reel 42)
    Originals in Box 124 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1976-1977 (Film R-7438, Reel 43)
  - Minutes, 1978-1979 (Film R-7438, Reel 44)
    Originals in Box 125 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1980 (Film R-7438, Reel 45)
    Originals in Boxes 113 and 125 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1981 (Film R-7438, Reel 46)
    Originals in Box 113 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, Jan 1982-Aug 1982 (Film R-7438, Reel 47)
    Originals in Box 126 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, Sep 1982-Dec 1982 (Film R-7438, Reel 48)
  - Minutes, 1983-1985 (Film R-7438, Reel 49)
    Originals in Boxes 126-127 (Researchers must use microfilm)
  - Minutes, 1986-1989 (Box 127)
  - Handwritten Minutes, 1994-2000 (incomplete) (Box 127)
  - Material for Inclusion in 1986 Minutes (includes copy of 1985 minutes), 1985-1986 (Box 7)
  - Material for Inclusion in 1986 Minutes (Box 8)
  - Material for Inclusion in 1988 Minutes (includes copy of 1987 minutes), 1987-1988 (Box 113)
  - Material for Inclusion in 1989 Minutes (includes copy of 1988 minutes), Meeting Materials (including minutes) (Jan-Apr 1990), 1988-Apr 1990 (Box 8)
  - Meeting Materials (including minutes), May 1990-Jul 1991 (Box 9)
  - Meeting Materials (including minutes), Aug 1991-Jun 1992 (Box 10)
  - Meeting Materials (including minutes), Jul 1992-Aug 1992 (Box 114)
  - Meeting Materials (including minutes), Sep 1992-1993 (Box 11)
  - Meeting Materials (including minutes), 1994-Jul 1995 (Box 12)
  - Meeting Materials (including minutes), Aug 1995-1996 (Box 13)
  - Meeting Materials (including minutes), 1997-Feb 1998 (Box 14)
  - Meeting Materials (including minutes), Mar 1998-Mar 1999 (Box 15)
  - Meeting Materials (including minutes), Apr 1999-Dec 1999 (Box 16)
  - Meeting Attendance Book, 1943-1945 (Box 119)
  - Meeting Attendance Books, 1982-2000 (Box 129)
- Series II: President's Office Files, 1967-2003
  Series II: President's Office Files, 1967-2003 Series III: Secretary's Office Files, 1960s-early 2000s includes correspondence, contracts, and subject files primarily from the 1980s-1990s under Secretary Bill Moriarity. includes correspondence, subject files, and International Executive Board material primarily covering the administrations of John Glasel (1983-1992) and Bill Moriarity (1993-2003).
  - Computer Committee and International Executive Board, 1994-1996 (Box 16)
  - International Executive Board Minutes, Lawsuit Against Steven Scott Enterprises, and Strategic Planning, 1996-2000 (Box 17)
  - Legal Files: A-G, late 1980s-late 1990s (Box 17)
  - Legal Files: G-T, late 1980s-2003 (Box 18)
  - Organizing, Pamphlet B, and Booking Agents, mid 1990s (Box 18)
  - Pamphlet B, Dick Gabriel, Mark Heter, Christine Maggo, Jim McGall, Advisory Committee, Assistance Program for Casual Musicians, Audio-Visual, Musicians Union of Australia, Canadian Broadcasting, Class A Scales, Western Conference, Convention (1997), Convention (1999), Electronic Press Kit, Escrow Accounts, Expense Reports, Film Negotiations, Health and Wellness, Incidental Music, International Executive Board, Investigation Task Force, Jingle Negotiations, Grievance Handling and Arbitration, Liability Insurance, Motion Picture Joint Cooperative Committee, Non-Standard Pay TV Agreement, Pamphlet F, and Federation Prescription Plan, 1970-1999 (bulk 1990s) (Box 19)
  - President's Advisory Committee, Public Relations Task Force -- Hotels, Regionalization Committee, and Non-Union Touring Musical Shows, 1990s (Box 20)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1986 (Box 20)
  - International Executive Board Materials (mostly correspondence, some agendas and minutes), 1985-1986 (Box 20)
  - International Executive Board Materials (mostly correspondence, some agendas and minutes), 1987 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence: A-H, 1990s (Box 21)
  - Correspondence: H-N, 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence: N-U, 1990s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence: V-Z, 1990s (Box 24)
  - Subject Files: A, 1980s-1990s (Box 24)
  - Subject Files: A-C, 1980s-1990s (Box 25)
  - Subject Files: C-E, 1980s-1990s (Box 26)
  - Subject Files: E-G, 1980s-1990s (Box 27)
  - Public Relations Task Force, American Federation of Musicians and Employers Pension Fund, and Correspondence, 1995-1997 (Box 27)
  - American Federation of Musicians and Employers Pension Fund, Public Relations Task Force, Pamphlet B, and AFM Canada Correspondence, 1993-1997 (Box 28)
  - Legislative Committee, Phonograph Record Label Agreement, Renovation, Theatre Sick Pay, United States Department of Labor, and Correspondence, 1975-1997 (bulk 1990-1997) (Box 29)
  - Recording Department, Recording Musicians Association, New York Pops, Organization of Union Representatives (OUR), Radio City Music Hall, Circuses, and International Executive Board, 1980s-1996 (Box 30)
  - Conferences, Conventions, Meetings, International Executive Board, and Lou (Russ) Russo, 1986-1989 (Box 31)
  - International Executive Board, late 1980s (Box 32)
  - Subject Files: N-S, late 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 32)
  - Subject Files: S-Z, late 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 33)
  - National Labor Relations Board and Credit Union, 1967-1986 (Box 33)
  - Subject Files: A-B, mid 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 33)
  - Subject Files: Building Committee, Legislation, Kingsborough Community College, Local 153, Music Performance Trust Funds (MPTF), and Other Material, 1990s (Box 34)
  - Cabaret Law, L. 802 Arbitration with League of American Theatres and Producers, Credit Union, Light Opera of Manhattan (LOOM), and Individuals Files, 1980s-1990s (Box 35)
  - Subject Files: G-H, mid 1980s-early 1990s (Box 35)
  - Subject Files: H-J, M-R, early 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 36)
  - Recording Department and Welfare Fund, 1983, 1993 (Box 37)
  - Subject Files: L-N, mid 1970s-late 1980s (Box 37)
  - Subject Files: N-R, mid 1970s-late 1980s (Box 38)
  - Subject Files: R-S, mid 1970s-late 1980s (Box 39)
  - Anne Walker Files: Radio City Music Hall, G. Harrell, and Music Copyists, early 1990s-mid 1990s (Box 39)
  - Anne Walker Files: Grand Hotel, early 1990s-mid 1990s (Box 40)
- Series III: Secretary's Office Files, 1960s-early 2000s
  Series III: Secretary's Office Files, 1960s-early 2000s includes correspondence, contracts, and subject files primarily from the 1980s-1990s under Secretary Bill Moriarity.
  - Correspondence: A-C, mid 1980s-late 1980s (Box 40)
  - Correspondence: C-F (mostly contracts), mid 1980s-late 1980s (Box 41)
  - Correspondence: F-T, mid 1980s-late 1980s (Box 42)
  - Correspondence: X-Z, mid 1980s-late 1980s (Box 43)
  - Subject Files: A-C, mid 1980s-early 1990s (Box 43)
  - Subject Files: C-I, mid 1980s-early 1990s (Box 44)
  - Subject Files: I-N, mid 1980s-early 1990s (Box 45)
  - Subject Files: N-S, mid 1980s-early 1990s (Box 46)
  - Subject Files: S-Z, mid 1980s-early 1990s (Box 47)
  - Subject Files: E-I, 1986-1987 (Box 47)
  - Subject Files: J-Z, 1986-1987 (Box 48)
  - Litigation File: B-N, mid 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 49)
  - Litigation File: S-W, mid 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 50)
  - Membership Correspondence: A-Z, 1989 (Box 50)
  - Membership Correspondence: A-H, 1988 (Box 50)
  - Membership Correspondence: I-Z, 1988 (Box 51)
  - Collective Bargaining Agreements: A-J, 1973-mid 1990s (Box 51)
  - Collective Bargaining Agreements: J-T, early 1980s-late 1990s (Box 52)
  - Contracts and Executive Board Correspondence, 1960s-1980s (Box 53)
  - Contracts, 1960s-1980s (Box 54)
  - Booking Agents and Lester Petrillo Memorial Fund for Disabled Musicians, mid 1980s-early 1990s (Box 55)
  - Correspondence: A-C, mid 1980s-1991 (Box 55)
  - Correspondence: C-H (mostly contracts), mid 1980s-1991 (Box 56)
  - Correspondence: I-Z, mid 1980s-1991 (Box 57)
  - Correspondence: M-V, mid 1990s-early 2000s (Box 57)
  - Correspondence: W-Z, mid 1990s-early 2000s (Box 58)
  - Correspondence: A-C (mostly contracts), early 1980s-1990 (Box 58)
  - Correspondence: C (mostly contracts), early 1980s-1990 (Box 59)
  - Correspondence: C-F (mostly contracts), mid 1980s-1988 (bulk 1988) (Box 59)
  - Correspondence: G-Z, mid 1980s-1988 (bulk 1988) (Box 60)
- Series IV: Concert Department Files, 1950s-1990s
  Series IV: Concert Department Files, 1950s-1990s documents the contract negotiations between Local 802 and various New York City symphonies, operas, and ballets.
  - Contract Negotiations: Brooklyn Academy of Music, Brooklyn Opera Society, and Brooklyn Philharmonic, 1970s-1980s (Box 60)
  - Contract Negotiations: New York City Opera, Joffrey Ballet, and Radio City Music Hall, 1970s-1980s (Box 61)
  - Contract Negotiations: Long Island Symphony Orchestra, Metropolitan Opera, and New York City Ballet, 1970s-1980s (Box 62)
  - Contract Negotiations: New York City Ballet, New York City Opera, and New York Philharmonic, 1970s-1980s (Box 63)
  - Contract Negotiations: New York Philharmonic and Westbury Music Fair, 1940s-1980s (Box 64)
  - Contract Negotiations: New York City Ballet, Metropolitan Opera, New York Philharmonic, and New York City Opera, 1990s (Box 65)
  - Contract Negotiations: New York City Ballet, Long Island Symphony, and City Center of Music and Drama, 1950s-1980s (Box 66)
- Series V: General Files, 1922-2010